<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emute Lab</title>
    <description>A Music Informatics and Performance Technologies Lab based in the School of Media, Film and Music at the University of Sussex</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 21:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 21:32:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Emute Lab 2 @ The Rosehill</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/Emutelab 2 Small.png&quot; alt=&quot;EMuTeLab2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emute Lab presents: an evening of audiovisual experimentation, with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derek Holzer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Duff&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex Peverett&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;qgb&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rose Hill, Brighton, 19th October, 7:30pm-11pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£6 (£4 students, concessions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tickets are available in advance from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ticketsource.co.uk/date/552827&quot;&gt;https://www.ticketsource.co.uk/date/552827&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/2128610264080293/&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/events/2128610264080293/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;derek-holzer&quot;&gt;Derek Holzer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derek Holzer (USA 1972) is a sound + light artist based in Helsinki &amp;amp; Berlin, whose current interests include DIY electronics, audiovisual instrument building, the relationship between sound and space, media archaeology, and participatory art forms. He has performed live, taught workshops and created scores of unique instruments and installations since 2002 across Europe, North and South America, and New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/202910465&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://macumbista.net&quot;&gt;http://macumbista.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/macumbista&quot;&gt;https://vimeo.com/macumbista&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;andrew-duff&quot;&gt;Andrew Duff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Duff is a sound artist and organiser of the University of Sussex based Brighton Modular meet. Since the late 1980s, Andrew has amassed a large collection of electronic music, and collected, modified and experimented with a range of, generally, Japanese analogue synthesizers, DJing, recording music and performing live at club nights and various other events. Since completing a Masters in Design and Digital Media in 2000, he has been involved in teaching, academic research, and continues to develop his own work. Since 2012 his work has been largely based around the use of a eurorack modular synthesiser and modified Vectrex games console for audio/visual and performance based vector oscillographics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kzBtUrvw0Js&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://andrew-duff.co.uk/&quot;&gt;http://andrew-duff.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/allthesixes666/&quot;&gt;https://www.instagram.com/allthesixes666/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/halfofmeis333&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/user/halfofmeis333&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alex-peverett&quot;&gt;Alex Peverett&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex Peverett: more info soon…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;qgb&quot;&gt;qgb&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;qgb is an an up and coming producer and artist local to Brighton. His work blends influences from his studies in audiovisual art at Sussex University with a love for UK dance music and its visceral quality. Exploring ideas from his debut album Hornets, the set combines algorithmic sequencing, hardware instruments and hyper-digital synthesis. Expect colourful soundscapes, treacherous rhythms, rumbling sub-bass, and striking visual accompaniments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tVzjqXOmJsE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/qgb/qgb-live-at-the-rose-hill&quot;&gt;https://soundcloud.com/qgb/qgb-live-at-the-rose-hill&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bleep.com/release/103083-qgb-hornets&quot;&gt;https://bleep.com/release/103083-qgb-hornets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab2</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>improvisation</category>
        
        <category>audiovisual</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Emute Lab 1 @ The Rosehill</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/emute1_webFlyer_noText_landscape_sm.png&quot; alt=&quot;EMuTeLab1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; :::::  May 23 - 7.30pm The Rosehill, Brighton :::::   &lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Emute Lab Presents … an evening of free strings and string free pedals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join us at The Rose Hill for a set of three duos from some of the UK’s fiercest improvisers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hannah Marshall (cello) &amp;amp; Otto Willberg (double bass)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seth Bennett (double bass) &amp;amp; Alice Eldridge (cello)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Noise Peddlar - Danny Bright &amp;amp; Lee Westwood - no input pedalboards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.therosehill.co.uk&quot;&gt;The Rose Hill&lt;/a&gt;, Brighton. £5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Emute Lab Presents …  is a space for sharing the ongoing research and practice of Emute Lab members and collaborators.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hannah Marshall (cello) &amp;amp; Otto Willberg (double bass)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A duo that has been finding an improvised language of rich sonic, textural and rhythmic counterpoint over the last year with performances at Fizzle - Birmingham, Bristol Music Club, Flim Flam - London and Fuse Arts Space - Bradford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hannah Marshall&lt;/b&gt;
I experiment with approaches to playing the ‘Cello using improvisation as a means to explore sound, music and performance. I play with a range of experimental groups and projects in the UK and Europe. I also collaborate with other performers and artists who work in mediums including theatre, performance, dance, storytelling and film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Ask your ears :] Exploring sonic territories and visiting musical antipodes, demonstrating an esoteric approach to instrumentation that is truly unique&lt;/em&gt;”- DreamCraeft recommendation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;with Marshall’s impeccable timing and skill for finding strong yet subtle gestures…&lt;/em&gt; ” “&lt;em&gt;..Vicious!.&lt;/em&gt;”- Dan Warburton&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Hannah Marshall has proven herself to be a solo player of imagination and intelligence; recording an album of deceptively simple but very rewarding and hypnotic music. A series of small meals that combine in a feast for the ears and mind.&lt;/em&gt;” - ears for eyes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/je2V2a53RYM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Otto Willberg&lt;/b&gt; is an improvising musician and composer, who mostly plays the double bass. His obsessive, and slightly unhinged tape Got Gills? is issued this July on Slip, and is his first release with the imprint. He plays with multiple groups around the UK, and has recently toured NYC and the States with guitarist David Birchall, and psych outfit Desmadrados Soldados de Ventura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GHU2jB5-mak&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Duot: Seth Bennett (double bass) &amp;amp; Alice Eldridge (cello)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Seth Bennett&lt;/b&gt; is one of the U.K.’s pre-eminent improvising double bass players. Currently based in rural Perthshire, his work involves free improvisation and composition for improvisers. Recent works include En Bas Quartet, a low string quartet for improvisers, all lovers are the song, a suite of six pieces for string trio and voice, and contributions to several recorded works, including CD releases by improvising sextet Sloth Racket, the Julie Tippets/Martin Archer Ensemble, Orchestre Tout Puissant Marcel Duchamp, and the large ensemble Favourite Animals. In addition, he maintains a busy performance schedule in Britain and across Europe in Jazz, Free Improvisation, English Folk music, and Contemporary Classical settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gFhNe-YtVm4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Alice Eldridge&lt;/b&gt; is a cellist and researcher working across sound, technology and ecology in scientific and creative domains. As an improvising cellist her intuitive, exploratory character has led to collaborations with some of europe’s most adventurous musicians at the  intersections of contemporary classical, folk, jazz, minimal pop, algorithmic and feedback musics. Recent collaborations and guest appearances include premiere performances of Seth Bennett’s En Bas Quartet, Julie Kjaer’s &lt;em&gt;This is Where You See Me&lt;/em&gt; and John Russell’s &lt;em&gt;The Narrative&lt;/em&gt;. She is 1/4 of all female multi-arts collective, Collectress, 1/2 of Feedback Cell, an ongoing experiment in open-ended hybrid luthiary and a regular at John Russell’s Fete Quaqua and Brighton’s Safehouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/180304450&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/api/player.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/180304450&quot;&gt;Alice Eldridge at Fete QuaQua 2016&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/user54602909&quot;&gt;Jack&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Noise Peddler&lt;/b&gt; (Danny Bright + Lee Westwood): two pedalboards, four amplifiers, and no inputs. Noise Peddler perform part-composed, part-improvised sounds generated and manipulated by guitar pedals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vXu1KTFuDdM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Danny Bright&lt;/b&gt; is a composer, sound designer, recordist, and sonic manipulator working across the fields of music, performance, installation, theatre and media. His practice explores the boundaries between sound/music/noise and space/place/memory; he is currently developing multi-modal compositional, performance, critical and installation work investigating sonic temporalities and auditory ‘ghostings’. Danny performs on guitar, samplescapes, tape, text/voice, and electronics as an ensemble member/leader, solo artist and improviser. He also works as a sound designer and composer for internationally recognised arts, theatre and media companies, and as a producer, recordist, sound technologist and engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Described by the Musician’s Union as “one of the UK’s most exciting and versatile musicians”, &lt;b&gt;Lee Westwood&lt;/b&gt; is a guitarist and composer whose wide-ranging output stems from a long-term tenacity for musical exploration. Far from ordinary, Lee’s works range from the Geometry-Music crossover of his multimedia exhibition ‘A Hidden Order’ (Saatchi Gallery, Athr, SCOPE) to a vast back-catalogue of works for solo guitar; from headlining festival stages with Hip-Hop groups and Prog Folk acts (Dizraeli &amp;amp; The Small Gods; Le Juki) to commissions from some of the UK’s leading ensembles and choirs (LSO, WUE; Musarc; Riot Ensemble; Notes Inégales). – &lt;a href=&quot;www.lee-westwood.com&quot;&gt;www.lee-westwood.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab1</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>improvisation</category>
        
        <category>NIME</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>EMuTeLab @ Seeing Sound - Report</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.seeingsound.co.uk&quot;&gt;Seeing Sound&lt;/a&gt; is a biannual symposium on audiovisual art, which took place at Bath Spa University in March.  This year two EMuTeLab members were presenting their work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;andrew-duff-i-dont-think-anyone-has-been-electrocuted-yet-sharing-info-online-to-modify-an-old-games-console-for-vector-oscillographics&quot;&gt;Andrew Duff: &lt;em&gt;I don’t think anyone has been electrocuted yet: Sharing info online to modify an old games console for vector oscillographics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/duff_seeingsound.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Andrew Duff presentation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract: &lt;em&gt;Since sharing a pdf online about how to modify a Vectrex (an early 1980s vector-based games console) to directly take in three audio signals to draw directly on the screen as one would with an oscilloscope, I have unwittingly become a ‘go-to guy’ with regards to entering the world of vector oscillographics. I have since been invited to talk at various electronic music events and am regularly contacted with requests for support, information and recommendations on appropriate modules. All the while the games console itself becomes harder to find on the second-hand market as they are perhaps becoming something of a cult artefact sought after by both gamers and electronic artists/musicians alike.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Vectrex offers a unique visual experience rarely found in standard oscilloscopes; it utilises three inputs for x, y and z control of the electron beam, is monochromatic, and the screen is relatively large. It does, however have its own idiosyncrasies, which makes for an interesting tool to work and perform with.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This talk will present a brief contextual history of experiments in this field with some examples of influential oscillographic artists such as Ben Laposky &amp;amp; Herbert W. Franke, followed by an overview of the impact sharing this pdf has had with examples of work by a range of current artists, experimentalists and performers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew’s talk was part of a wider Vectrex theme at Seeing Sound, with other presentations from Derek Holzer and Douglas Nunn.  You can find his slides on his website &lt;a href=&quot;http://users.sussex.ac.uk/~ad207/adweb/assets/seeingsound2018slides.pdf&quot;&gt;http://users.sussex.ac.uk/~ad207/adweb/assets/seeingsound2018slides.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chris-kiefer-10k-video&quot;&gt;Chris Kiefer: &lt;em&gt;10K Video&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/10kvideo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chris Kiefer 10K Video&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;10000 neural oscillators conspire to make a bad approximation of a one second video loop, while their internal networks are stretched and twisted by their own sound and their neighbours.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an improvised performance, where a video is resynthesised by an ensemble of neural conceptor networks, each of which has learnt (with varying degrees of success) to approximate the behaviour of an individual pixel in the original.  The ghostly result is manipulated live, to send this mass of miniature feedback systems into collective overdrive.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neural networks used in this piece are complex dynamical systems which need self-sustaining energy to continue their role; they follow a trajectory, but this trajectory can be manipulated and influenced, both between networks and from global forces; these networks can be damped, overdriven, distorted, leaked, excited, surprised, saturated and revitalised.  When revitalised in synchrony they can play a rendition of the original video loop.  When manipulated, this video can be distorted and effected in many directions.  During the piece, the host of networks are continually revitalised, and then manipulated along infinity varying trajectories towards noise or destruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris performed this new piece live.  You can see a generative version that runs in your web browser at &lt;a href=&quot;http://facingaway.luuma.net/&quot;&gt;http://facingaway.luuma.net/&lt;/a&gt; (fairly decent GPU needed)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/seeingsoundreport</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/seeingsoundreport</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>talk</category>
        
        <category>audiovisual</category>
        
        <category>music</category>
        
        <category>graphics</category>
        
        <category>machine learning</category>
        
        <category>vectrex</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ens Ekt Improvisation Workshop</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/260582432&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/260582432&quot;&gt;Ens Ekt @ SARC 1&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/user7828804&quot;&gt;Paul Stapleton&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; :::::  Friday June 1st,  1pm - 3pm @ Sussex Humanities Lab :::::   &lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ens Ekt will be visiting us as part of their UK tour for a practice based workshop on the nature and relevance for improvisation in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is improvisation?&lt;/em&gt;  We’re interested in what you think. How is it relevant for your own practice (regardless of discipline)? And how can you develop potential?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop format is liable to be subject to improvisation, but will likely follow a format such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ens Ekt will play an improvised set.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There will then be an open conversation concerning practice and improvisation, facilitated by the trio.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open Session. There will then be a session in which all are welcome to participate. As well as musicians we positively encourage those from other areas of interest (perhaps dance, drama, visual art or any other area).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event is free, but please register at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/ens-ekt-improvisation-workshop-emute-lab-tickets-45646588174&quot;&gt;eventbrite&lt;/a&gt; as spaces are limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adam Pultz Melbye&lt;/strong&gt; – double bass&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Simon Rose&lt;/strong&gt; – baritone saxophone&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Paul Stapleton&lt;/strong&gt; – bonsai sound sculpture (BoSS)  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ens Ekt features the experimental musical inventions of Paul Stapleton (Californian born, Belfast-based) placed in dialogue with the circular breathed multiphonics and harmonic textures of Simon Rose (English born, Berlin-based) and the resonant gestural and spectrally focused playing of Adam Pultz Melbye (Danish born, Berlin-based). The group explores emergent timbral, dynamic and social musical structures through improvisation. Having worked together more frequently in duo settings (see below), the trio configuration offers an opportunity to explore new modes of interactions in part facilitated by purpose built technologies that intertwine metallic, wooden and electronic resonances in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.paulstapleton.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/Ens-Ekt-01-900x450.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ensekt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ens Ekt will be playing a full set at &lt;a href=&quot;http://safehousebrighton.co.uk/2018/05/31/ens-ekt/&quot;&gt;Safehouse&lt;/a&gt; on May 31st.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/ensekt</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/ensekt</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>improvisation</category>
        
        <category>NIME</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Newhaven Soundcamp</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/westbeach.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;soundcamp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; :::::  May 5th - May 6th @ Newhaven Community Garden, Newhaven :::::   &lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join us for newhaven soundcamp over the International Dawn Chorus weekend of 5th to 6th May 2018, when small groups of people around the world will sleep outside and listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International Dawn Chorus Day is a world wide celebration of the dawn chorus initiated by the Wildlife Trusts to raise awareness of the deep importance of nature conservation and close relationship between human wellbeing and that of all other living species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newhaven Soundcamp is part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundtent.org/soundcamp_reveil.html&quot;&gt;REVEIL&lt;/a&gt;, an network of open mics around the world. Instigated by arts collective &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundtent.org/soundcamp_about.html&quot;&gt;soundcamp&lt;/a&gt;, REVEIL curates a live radio broadcast from these listening points as the sun rises around the globe on the International Dawn Chorus weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newhaven Soundcamp is a small scale event for local residents to act as a simple, potent point for ecological, social, intellectual, aesthetic and spiritual engagement with the soundscape of Newhaven. It links this spot on Sussex Downs Biosphere (The Living Coast) to an international network of site of ecological and sonic interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The broadcast will be made using a DIY radio transmitter constructed from a raspberry Pi and will feature on the Resonance FM broadcast early on Sunday morning - or check out links below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Links:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/soundcamp-newhaven-tickets-45174650596&quot;&gt;Further information and free tickets&lt;/a&gt; for Newhaven Soundcamp&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://soundtent.org/soundcamp_listen.html&quot;&gt;listen to the curated stream on International Dawn Chorus Day&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Listen in to the Newhaven mic on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://locusonus.org/soundmap/051/&quot;&gt;locussonus sound map&lt;/a&gt; - this will be streaming all weekend&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More about &lt;a href=&quot;soundtent.org&quot;&gt;Soundcamp&lt;/a&gt; and links other soundcamps around the world&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://paper.dropbox.com/doc/Streaming-Workshop-Brighton-Digital-Festival-Onca-Gallery-12-10-17-0SoIwneySy7FLeixfsveP&quot;&gt;Information on building your own DIY radio transmitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://paper.dropbox.com/doc/Solar-power-for-off-grid-streaming-JF9LIMXwqMeH19twsrX3U&quot;&gt;Further info on solar panels for off grid streaming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelivingcoast.org.uk&quot;&gt;The Living Coast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://growingtogethernewhaven.org/&quot;&gt;Newhaven Community garden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 3, Prof Almo Farina will be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.emutelab.org/blog/almoFarina&quot;&gt;giving a talk&lt;/a&gt; on his pioneering work in Ecoacoustics - all welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented in association with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelivingcoast.org.uk/&quot;&gt;The Living Coast&lt;/a&gt;, kindly hosted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://growingtogethernewhaven.org/&quot;&gt;Growing Together Newhaven&lt;/a&gt; and supported by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/shl/&quot;&gt;Sussex Humanities Lab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/soundcamp</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/soundcamp</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>ecoacoustics</category>
        
        <category>DIY tech</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Seminar: Gianluca Memoli and Spyros Polychronopoulos (Interact Lab, Informatics)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;::::: Thursday, April 26th, 2018. 2-4pm - Recital Room (Falmer House 120) :::::&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two talks from members of the Interact Lab at Sussex, who are both researchers in Acoustic Levitation and Human Computer Interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spyros-polychronopoulos-new-ways-to-create-and-deliver-music&quot;&gt;Spyros Polychronopoulos: New ways to create and deliver music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spolychronopoulos.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spyros Polychronopoulos&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aesthetics of dead (as pre-recorded) and live (as endless unique reproduced) music. Challenging the “here and now” of the work of art with programmable performers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/reference/subject/philosophy/works/ge/benjamin.htmhttps://www.marxists.org/reference/subject/philosophy/works/ge/benjamin.htm&quot;&gt;Walter Benjamin (1936)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://emporium.room40.org/products/583176-spyros-polychronopoulos-live-electronic-music-sound-object&quot;&gt;Live Electronic Music Sound Object (2016)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/docs/Music perception and the fluctuation of utopia.pdf&quot;&gt;Music perception and the fluctuation of utopia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bio&quot;&gt;Bio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spyros Polychronopoulos was born in Athens, Greece in 1980. His interest in sound, both as a physical phenomenon as well as a form of art, began at an early age. He holds a degree in Physics and a PhD in Electrical Engineering from University of Patras, Greece. His thesis focused on tuning the acoustics of closed spaces and he has published a number of papers in this field. After relocating to London in 2014, he gained three years of practical experience working as an acoustic consultant. Further to his research in sound, he has developed unique sound objects, released 15 albums and performed a number of concerts around the world. Spyros regularly leads workshops and lectures discussing the new technologies in composition and aesthetics of sound. He currently works as a Research Fellow in the Informatics Department at the University of Sussex, UK, researching ‘Human-computer Interaction for Acoustic Levitation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gianluca-memoli-spatial-sound-using-meta-materials&quot;&gt;Gianluca Memoli: Spatial Sound using Meta-materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/gmemoli.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gianluca Memoli&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an architect, a sound engineer or a theatre director designs the acoustics of a space, the presence of sound is binary: it is either there for everyone or not. We manage light differently, though: well-established technologies allows us to exploit light and shadows, beams that follow characters, diffused or focused spotlights. The technology for achieving similar results with sound is simply not there: since directional speakers still don’t maintain their promises in terms of performance, large arrays of speakers are still used for beam-forming, either software controlled or spatially arranged. In this talk, I will discuss the opportunities offered by acoustic meta-materials to achieve spatial control on sound in static applications. These can be placed in front of loudspeakers just like lenses or filters would be positioned in front of a light source, for achieving diffraction-limited effects. I will also discuss where, in my opinion, these new tools may lead us in the short and medium term and whether they will eventually give us the same control on sound that we have on light, across all the frequency range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bio-1&quot;&gt;Bio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gianluca has worked in acoustics for 14 years, after his PhD. His acoustic research (soundscapes, industrial and medical ultrasound) has taken him to influence EU legislation and ISO standards, to work with local authorities and hospitals, to measure the largest bubble in the word and to find new ways to prolong shelf life of honey using ultrasound. He is a passionate science communicator and has worked with creatives of all sorts, from garden designers to choreographers.  As a newly appointed lecturer in Informatics at Sussex, he is currently looking at ways to give creatives the same control on sound that they have on light using specially engineered, 3D-printed, passive materials.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/interactLabSeminar</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/interactLabSeminar</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>talk</category>
        
        <category>acoustics</category>
        
        <category>3D printing</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Perspectives in Ecoacoustics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;::::: Thursday, May 3rd, 2018. 4pm - Sussex Humanities Lab :::::&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Talk: Perspectives in Ecoacoustics – Prof Almo Farina, University of Urbino, Italy&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to welcome Prof Almo Farina, a naturalist and landscape ecologist and one of the pioneers of Ecoacoustics - the investigation of the ecological role of sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/shl/&quot;&gt;Sussex Humanities Lab&lt;/a&gt; (Silverstone Building, SB211) - All welcome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/farina_ALMO_FARINA.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Farina&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you are happy, your voice is more fresh. When you are tired or annoyed, it changes. The same applies to the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;perspectives-in-ecoacoustics-a-contribution-to-defining-a-discipline&quot;&gt;Perspectives in Ecoacoustics: A contribution to defining a discipline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ecoacoustics is a recently established discipline that investigates the ecological role of sounds. A set of processes in four [&lt;em&gt;adaptive, behavioural, geographical, ecosemiotic&lt;/em&gt;] domains supports and guides the development of ecoacoustics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;adaptive&lt;/em&gt;  domain includes evolutionary mechanisms that join sound typology with the physical and biological characteristics of the environment and create frequency partitioning among species to reduce competition.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The behavioural  domain addresses interspecific signals associated with geophysical and anthropogenic sounds that operate to shape temporary acoustic communities and orient species to select suitable acoustic habitats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The geographic  domain pertains to the geography of sound, an entity composed of three subordinate acoustic objects: sonotopes, soundtopes, and sonotones, which are operationally delimited in a geographical and temporal space by the distribution of the ecoacoustic events. The ecoacoustic events allow the classification of complex configurations/patterns of acoustic signals and represent the grain of a soundscape mosaic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ecosemiotic  domain operates by  communication mechanisms within the species level according to a function-specific perception of the acoustic information facilitated by encoding/decoding processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long-term monitoring, habitat health, biodiversity assessment, soundscape conservation and ecosystem management makes ecoacoustics relevant in several fields where human intrusion in ecosystems is growing at an unprecedented rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/farina_SET.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;recorder&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;SET – Soundscape Explorer [Terrestrial]) digital recorder. Photo: Almo Farina&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;biography&quot;&gt;Biography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almo Farina is an Italian naturalist and Professor of Ecology in the Department of Pure and Applied Sciences, Urbino University, Italy. He has dedicated the last ten years to elaborate new theories in landscape ecology, soundscape ecology and ecoacoustics. He considers the protection of the biological diversity integrated with the human cultural heritage and well-being, a priority of its scientific and human mission. In 2014 Almo was elected the first President of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/ecoacousticssociety/&quot;&gt;International Society of Ecoacoustics&lt;/a&gt;, and in 2015 he founded the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iinsteco.org/&quot;&gt;International Institute of Ecoacoustics&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wiley.com/en-gb/Ecoacoustics:+The+Ecological+Role+of+Sounds-p-9781119230694&quot;&gt;Ecoacoustics: The Ecological Role of Sounds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Editor-in-Chief of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.veruscript.com/journals/journal-of-ecoacoustics/&quot;&gt;Journal of Ecoacoustics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jmecology.com/&quot;&gt;Journal of Mediterranean Ecology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codebiology.org/&quot;&gt;Code Biology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented in association with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/shl/&quot;&gt;Sussex Humanities Lab&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/ssrp/&quot;&gt;Sussex Sustainability Research Programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May 5 &amp;amp; 6 is International Dawn Chorus day. Join us for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.emutelab.org/blog/soundcamp&quot;&gt;Newhaven Soundcamp&lt;/a&gt; or listen in to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundtent.org/soundcamp_listen.html&quot;&gt;live stream&lt;/a&gt; of dawn chorus as it spreads across planet with the rising sun.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/almoFarina</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/almoFarina</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>talk</category>
        
        <category>ecoacoustics</category>
        
        <category>acoustic ecology</category>
        
        <category>soundscape</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Thousand Mindreaders</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;::::: Thursday, March 15th, 2018 @ Caxton Arms, 6:30 pm :::::&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Where: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.caxtonarms.co.uk&quot;&gt;Caxton Arms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
36 North Gardens &lt;br /&gt;
Brighton.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;NOTE: This event was supposed to be in the SHL, but due to the USS STRIKE it is now running it as part of the exiting &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ywtMO06wlxqRXftEGwpUUZQhtXwCyS_i6qWLMW43_eA/edit&quot;&gt;SussexforUSS&lt;/a&gt; events&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; ALL WELCOME !&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magician and Human-Machine Interactor &lt;a href=&quot;http://stuartnolan.com&quot;&gt;Stuart Nolan&lt;/a&gt; will be giving a workshop in mindreading, followed by talk on his practice as a magician. Stuart has a track record in training mindreading skills in an hour, so it is certainly worth coming to this session to learn this important art. Join us at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.caxtonarms.co.uk&quot;&gt;Caxton Arms&lt;/a&gt; Pub - All welcome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/mindreaders.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MindReaders&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Workshop: One Thousand Mindreaders (6:30-7:30 pm)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One Thousand Mindreaders is a year-long collaborative artwork during which the artist Stuart Nolan will train one thousand new mindreaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants will learn the skill of muscle reading, sensing the small subconscious movements of another person’s hands. This will enable them to recreate drawings that another person is merely thinking of.
They will also learn how to find objects that another person has hidden in a room or building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the drawings and the found objects will be exhibited in 2019 and trainee mindreaders will be offered the opportunity to demonstrate their new skills for a public audience at a series of performances throughout 2018 and 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this interactive session, we will also explore the role of touch in interaction, learning to read each other’s minds using techniques based on Victorian mindreading tricks, games, and experiments, and improved with current research into the neuroscience of touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Talk: Beyond The Feelies (8 pm)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Of all our senses, touch is the one considered least deceptive and the most secure.’ - René Descartes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Touch is the most intimate and emotional of the senses. It is no accident that when we speak of affecting someone emotionally we say we have touched them. We feel emotions and we feel each other’s joy and pain. Touch is central when negotiating issues of trust, veracity, falsehood, agency, difference, and connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the essay Silence is Golden, Aldous Huxley wrote of his disgust with the coming of sound to film. He parodied the “talkies” in Brave New World by imagining a future where film would include a sense of touch, “Going to the Feelies this evening, Henry?… There’s a love scene on a bearskin rug; they say it’s marvelous. Every hair of the bear reproduced. The most amazing tactual effects…” This crude idea of touch as something that is separate to film distracts us from the fact that cinema has always been a bodily, visceral experience. This is true of all media but becomes more visible with interaction, VR, haptics, and immersion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this interactive session, we will explore the role of touch in interaction, learning to read each other’s minds using techniques based on Victorian mindreading tricks, games, and experiments, and improved with current research into the neuroscience of touch. Stuart will give a brief insight into his recent work on touch in healthcare, theatre, dance, sport, robotics, and 5G and we will explore the potential of technology to capture, measure, and transmit touch data in mediated communication, interaction, art, and storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/stuart.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MindReaders&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further Info:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;www.stuartnolan.com&quot;&gt;www.stuartnolan.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;www.1000mindreaders.com&quot;&gt;www.1000mindreaders.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/1000mindreaders&quot;&gt;@1000Mindreaders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Instagram: onethousandmindreaders&lt;br /&gt;
Facebook: @OneThousandMindreaders&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/mindreaders</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/mindreaders</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>performances</category>
        
        <category>mind reading</category>
        
        <category>HCI</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>BEER: Dark Matter at ACCA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;::::: Wednesday, February 21st, 2018 @ ACCA, 8pm :::::&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with the Attenborough Centre for the Creative Arts, we are organising an eventful day with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.beast.bham.ac.uk/offspring/beer/&quot;&gt;Birmingham Ensemble for Electroacoustic Research&lt;/a&gt; (BEER).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/BEER.png&quot; alt=&quot;BEER&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Performance&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This performance by the Birmingham Ensemble for Electroacoustic Research, created in collaboration with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://artcms.web.cern.ch/artcms/&quot;&gt;art@CMS&lt;/a&gt; project at CERN in Switzerland, involves the real-time sonification of data streams from the Large Hadron Collider, the world’s largest and most complex particle accelerator. Experimental data containing clues towards possible ‘new physics’ becomes the raw material for improvised music and visualisations programmed by the ensemble with an aim to creating a result that while beautiful, is also both musically and scientifically meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Workshop&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;::::: @ ACCA, 3-5pm :::::&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop for composers and artists explores the possibilities of using scientific data as a resource for music and sonic art, with particular focus on sonifying data from the Large Hadron Collider at CERN, the world’s largest particle accelerator. An introduction to the physics involved will be followed by an exploration of strategies for converting the data into sound. Previous experience of computer music environments is useful, but not required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places in the workshop are limited. Please sign up &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/forms/2cTbIecn62yPcwmf1&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/darkmatter.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dark Matter Workshop&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information about the event on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.attenboroughcentre.com/events/1643/dark-matter?spektrix_bounce=true&quot;&gt;ACCA website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/darkmatter</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/darkmatter</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>performances</category>
        
        <category>sonification</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>EMuTeLab 0 @ The Rose Hill, Brighton</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/emutelab0_webflyer.png&quot; alt=&quot;EMuTeLab0 Gig Flyer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Emute Lab presents… an evening of exciting experimental music&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join us at the Rose Hill club to experience some cutting-edge music with new exciting instruments and audiovisual technologies. On the bill are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JesterN (Laser Drawing / Modular Synth)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marije Baalman (Chrysalis / Installations)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brain Dead Ensemble (Thren0scope / Feedback Cellos / Feedback Double Bass)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;January 12th, 2018. 7pm. at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.therosehill.co.uk&quot;&gt;The Rose Hill&lt;/a&gt;, Brighton. £5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JesterN: Laser Drawing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JesterN’s Laser Drawing is a synesthetic experience in which you can listen to what you see, and see what you listen to
Using its modular synthesizer, JesterN manipulates electric voltages live, sending them in exactly the same way to the speakers to create sound and to the laser to create its curvy shapes with vivid colors. An artisanal live show in which every beat and every shape is simultaneously improvised on the stage. Being cooked on the spot, music-wise it depends on the space and on the vibe: it can go from drones, to harsh noise, from techno straight beats to IDM syncopations, or something completely diferent …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alberto Novello a.k.a. JesterN is a scientist, composer, sound and video artist. In his works, he has assisted Alvin Lucier, Nicholas Collins and Trevor Wishart. His artistic works have been presented in international festivals such as Amsterdam Dance Event, Venice Biennale, Impuls Tanz Vienna, Seoul International Music Festival, Emu Fest Roma, Monaco Electroacoustique, New York Computer Music Festival, Rewire Festival and conferences such as NIME, ICMC, ISMIR, ICMPC, ICA, ICCE and ESSEM and institutes for contemporary music research such as CCMAS in Mexico, GRM in France, Logos Foundation in Belgium, STEIM Amsterdam, IEM Graz, OMI New York, the Royal Conservatory of Den Haag, Conservatory of Padua.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jestern.com/&quot;&gt;http://www.jestern.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/235351838&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/235351838&quot;&gt;JesterN Laser Drawing @AESON Festival 2017&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/jestern&quot;&gt;jestern&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Marije Baalman&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cocoon lies on stage, barely recognisable in the dim light. Slow tones are sounding in the space. The light seems to change color – the tones are changing slowly in pitch. The cocoon seems to move – the light seems to get brighter and gradually shift color. Suddenly a fast movement – a shrieking sound fills the space – then again everything quiets down – the movement, the sound, the light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chrysalis is a performative environment where the focus is on slow movements – becoming aware of the minimal movements of the body, both conscious and unconscious movements. It is about interaction on a long timescale – involving multiple senses (hearing, sight, haptic).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marije Baalman is an artist and researcher/developer working in the field of interactive sound art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marijebaalman.eu/&quot;&gt;https://www.marijebaalman.eu/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/183344106&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/183344106&quot;&gt;Chrysalis - a teaser&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/user16929243&quot;&gt;Marije Baalman&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Brain Dead Ensemble&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Brain Dead Ensemble consists of members of the Emute Lab interested in feedback in acoustic and electronic instruments, and the combination of those. The audiovisual live coding instrument, Threnoscope, will feed sound directly into the acoustic instruments (two cellos and a double bass) via their mechanical actuators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thor Magnusson (Threnoscope, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ixi-audio.net/&quot;&gt;http://www.ixi-audio.net/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanos Polymeneas Liontiris (Feedback Bass, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thanospl.net/&quot;&gt;http://thanospl.net/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alice Eldridge&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Kiefer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Feedback Cell, Feedback Cellos, &lt;a href=&quot;http://feedbackcell.ooo/&quot;&gt;http://feedbackcell.ooo/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no video of the Brain Dead Ensemble (they have not figured out how to do that), but there are some of the Threnoscope, cello and bass (Thor, Alice and Thanos):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/179079463&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/179079463&quot;&gt;Fermata at OSC in Brighton&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/thormagnusson&quot;&gt;thormagnusson&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and two feedback cellos (Alice and Chris):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gazcpDOFTz0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; gesture=&quot;media&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab0</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab0</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>performances</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
