<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emute Lab</title>
    <description>A Music Informatics and Performance Technologies Lab based in the School of Media, Film and Music at the University of Sussex</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2019 08:33:37 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 May 2019 08:33:37 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sonic Writing - A book launch in the SHL</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:::: Thursday, March 14th, 5.00pm, @ The SHL, Sussex University ::::&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thor Magnusson’s book &lt;i&gt;Sonic Writing: Technologies of Material, Symbolic and Signal Inscriptions&lt;/i&gt; is now out with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/9781501313868&quot;&gt;Bloomsbury Academic&lt;/a&gt;. This monograph is the final outcome of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://ahrc.ukri.org&quot;&gt;AHRC&lt;/a&gt; funded &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonicwriting.org&quot;&gt;research project&lt;/a&gt; that ran between 2016 and 2018. The book is divided into four key parts: &lt;b&gt;instruments&lt;/b&gt; (material inscriptions), &lt;b&gt;notation&lt;/b&gt; (symbolic inscriptions), &lt;b&gt;recording&lt;/b&gt; (signal inscriptions), and &lt;b&gt;new music technologies&lt;/b&gt;, or how our analogue and electronic traditions are translated and applied in the design of digital instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book launch will be held in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/shl/&quot;&gt; Sussex Humanities Lab&lt;/a&gt; on March 14th - all welcome! In addition to drinks and snacks, there will be musical performances by Emute Lab colleagues: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.feedbackcell.info&quot;&gt;Feedback Cell&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://alexanderpeverett.com&quot;&gt;Alex Peverett&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://andrew-duff.co.uk&quot;&gt;Andrew Duff&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evelynficarra.net/about/&quot;&gt;Evelyn Ficarra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the music, Thor Magnusson will give a short introduction to the context of the book and Prof. Caroline Bassett, the director of the SHL, will respond with “Notes on Sonic Writing”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bloomsbury has a discount code that can be used on check-out when purchasing the book on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloomsbury.com/9781501313868&quot;&gt;Bloomsbury website&lt;/a&gt; : “GLR MP6”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;NOTE: As of March 1st, 2019, the book is out of print! - Bloomsbury is printing more and we will let people know when it is available again.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bloomsburycp3.codemantra.com/viewer/5c58b483713c090001cc13c9&quot;&gt;
&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;W3Schools&quot; src=&quot;/img/sonicwriting.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/sonicwriting</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/sonicwriting</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>book</category>
        
        <category>performance</category>
        
        <category>improvisation</category>
        
        <category>audiovisual</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SLATUR - Research from the Icelandic Academy of the Arts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:::: Friday, March 1st, 1pm, @ The Sussex Humanities Lab, Sussex University ::::&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A series of presentations from Iceland-based composers and artists working with electronic media and transdisciplinary practice, teaching at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lhi.is&quot;&gt;Iceland University of the Arts&lt;/a&gt;. The session will be followed by a short concert, starting at 2pm, with performances of pieces written by these composers on the new halldorophone instrument (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesper Pedersen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Title: Live performance with modular synths&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live performance with modular synthesizers can be a challenge. Even more so when performing solo. In this talk, Jesper will introduce his current hybrid live rig and demonstrate some of the performance capabilities of his DIY Serge modular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bio:&lt;/b&gt; Jesper Pedersen is a composer, performer, educator and DIYer based in Reykjavik. He studied Music Technology at Aalborg University in Denmark and has been developing experimental works that mixes DIY technology with acoustic musical instruments through the use of real time software based animated graphical notation. Recently he has been focussing on performing on modular synthesizers both solo and in collaborations such as the North Atlantic postcolonial outfit The Remains of the Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His works have been performed internationally by S.L.Á.T.U.R., Goodiepal and Pals, Duo Harpverk, Ensemble Adapter, the Iceland Symphony Orchestra, Ilan Volkov, Katie Buckley, Ingólfur Vilhjámsson at festivals including the Tectonics Festival, Nordlichter Biennale, Sonic Festival, OpenDays, Rainy Days, Summartónar, Raflost, Geiger, Sláturtíð, Dark Music Days and Nordic Music Days. 
Jesper is a part of the Icelandic composers collective S.L.Á.T.U.R. and pays the bills by teaching electronic music composition at the Iceland Academy of the Arts and the Kópavogur Computer Music Center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slatur.is/jesper&quot;&gt;www.slatur.is/jesper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.instagram.com/jespertralala&quot;&gt;www.instagram.com/jespertralala&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/jesper.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jesper Pedersen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sam Rees&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Title: Visual Noise, Discordant Clutter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam will present examples of his personal work with interactive dioramas using circuit-bent toy robots as well as his influences and current interests, from outsider art to voodoo shrines, scavenger populations and robot-human empathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bio: &lt;/b&gt; A generalist with a passion for DIY cultures, manifesting itself through printed matter, installation, workshops and events. British born, Sam studied interactive arts in Manchester in 2003, but has been living in Iceland for the last 6 years. He teaches interactive media at the Iceland University of the Arts, was a co-founder of the Fjúk arts residency in NE Iceland and co-organises the annual Reykjavik Zine and Print Fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent work focuses on a series of interactive dioramas - sequential narrative installations, eclectic assemblage with circuit bent toys, exploring technological waste and our perception of robotics. Recent activities include a residency at Signal Culture in upstate New York, and exhibitions at the Reykjavik Electronic Arts Festival and Nordic House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ififoundafrozentimewarpidputitinthemicrowaveatyourhouse.co.uk&quot;&gt;www.ififoundafrozentimewarpidputitinthemicrowaveatyourhouse.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://instagram.com/sam.t.rees&quot;&gt;http://instagram.com/sam.t.rees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/sam.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sam Rees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Áki Ásgeirsson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Title: About S.L.Á.T.U.R.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short introduction to few past projects of the Icelandic S.L.Á.T.U.R. group, including art and sport competitions, musical notation, costume design and cross-/trans-/non-disciplinary practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bio: &lt;/b&gt;Áki Ásgeirsson is a composer and multimedia artist from Garður, Iceland. He has written music for traditional instruments as well as designed new acoustic instruments, audio software, computer controlled instruments and sound installations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Áki has been active in the Icelandic experimental music/art scene as a composer, sound artist and performer. With background in free improvisation, electronic music, art coding and algorithmic music, Áki often works in collaboration with other artists of various fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is a member of composer collective S.L.Á.T.U.R. and co-organises the RAFLOST festival for electronic art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aki.is&quot;&gt;www.aki.is&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/aki.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aki Asgeirsson&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Halldór Úlfarsson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Augmented Halldorophone&lt;/strong&gt; 
(a short discussion in conjunction with the concert presentation)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A short talk about the exploration of the newest BELA equipped Halldorophone and writing a small piece of music for it. Sonic as well as technological obstacles encountered during the work will be discussed from the viewpoint of the composer’s role. The Halldorophone is the brainchild of Icelandic artist and instrument designer Halldór Úlfarsson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further info: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.halldorophone.info&quot;&gt;http://www.halldorophone.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/halldorophone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Halldorophone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/slatur</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/slatur</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>book</category>
        
        <category>performance</category>
        
        <category>improvisation</category>
        
        <category>audiovisual</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Emute Lab 3</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/EmuteLab3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;EmuteLab3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:::: Wednesday, Feb 13th, 7.30-11pm, @ The Rose Hill, Brighton ::::&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme will feature three acts exploring the interaction of sound and image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BOG BODIES - (Robert Stillman, Sean Carpio, Anders Holst)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bog Bodies sound breaks down distinctions between composition and improvisation, electronic and acoustic sound, abstraction and figure. Their distinctive musical style reflects the eclecticism of the band members’ individual careers (they have collaborated with artists such as Manuel Göttsching, Kit Downes, and Joachim Badenhorst), and to the broad range of music from which they take inspiration, which includes James Blood Ulmer, Sunn O))), Archie Shepp, and Supersilent. Their first album, ‘Sligo’ was released in 2017 on Migro Recordings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thor Magnusson ‘Threnoscope’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Threnoscope is a microtonal drone instrument that provides a context for improvisation of microtonal music where both the live coder and the instrumentalists influence the piece’s development. The Threnoscope is notated through live coding, with sound characteristics and speaker locations being visualised on a projected  graphical score. Musical notes move around the spectral and physical space, long in duration, and sculptable by the performer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roosa Poni&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roosa Poni is a collaborative band of &lt;a href=&quot;http://tehis.net&quot;&gt;Alo Allik &lt;/a&gt; and Delia Fano Yela. Allik is an Estonian sound artist who has performed his live coded electronic music and generative computer graphics throughout the world. His aesthetically and geographically restless lifestyle has enabled him to traverse a diverse range of musical worlds including DJ-ing electronic dance music, live electronic jam sessions, electroacoustic composition, free improvisation and audiovisual performances. He has forged collaborations with a number of curious and innovative musicians, writers and visual artists along the way focussed on exploring links between science, technology, creativity and tradition. In recent years he has been developing a musical style he describes as noisefunk which derives its form from ancient tribal rhythm patterns and its sonic nature from evolutionary synthesis algorithms. Currently, Alo works as a researcher, programmer and lecturer in London, while continuing to perform his music and visuals to audiences worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Koray Tahiroğlu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koray Tahiroğlu is a musician, Academy Research Fellow in the Department of Media, Aalto University School of ARTS. He is the founder and head of SOPI (Sound and Physical Interaction) research group. He practices art as a researcher focusing on digital musical interactions, as well as a performer of live electronic music. Since 2004, he has been also teaching workshops and courses introducing computational strategies and methodologies for artistic exploration of interactive music. Tahiroğlu has performed experimental music in collaboration as well as in solo performances in Europe, North America and Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/176701167&quot;&gt;https://vimeo.com/176701167&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tickets at the door, or even better, on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/emute-lab-3-tickets-55517138255?fbclid=IwAR1Hx8hsu0WjBbXuILO9aVdjIH4nYqPyUuyUZmoaX2TDDugqT5B_Nwu7KUA&quot;&gt;Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab3</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab3</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>improvisation</category>
        
        <category>audiovisual</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Art of Soldering Workshop</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/soldering.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ArtofSoldering&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:::: Friday, Nov 23rd, 12-2pm, @ Sussex Humanites Lab ::::&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Workshop Leader: Alex Peverett (SHL/Emute Lab)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soldering is an essential skill for the modern musician, creative practitioner and researcher whose academic interests may lead them to accessing and maintaining electronic equipment. This workshop will cover a hands-on introduction to soldering, wiring your own audio cables and building DIY contact microphones and hydrophones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact microphones enable us to access sounds that may otherwise seem hidden, picking up vibrations in material substances. They can also be used in building our own reverberation systems and for amplifying acoustic instruments. As hydrophones they can reveal whole new aquatic soundworlds for study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop on soldering serves as a good preparation for upcoming SHL/Emute DIWO workshops, which will include: DIY oscillators, Oscillographics and many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This open and friendly workshop is aimed at the absolute beginner, but will be helpful to the more advanced too. We encourage anyone of any background to sign up, so please visit the following link:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/the-art-of-soldering-cables-contact-microphones-and-hydrophones-tickets-52485642971&quot;&gt;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/the-art-of-soldering-cables-contact-microphones-and-hydrophones-tickets-52485642971&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/artofsoldering</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/artofsoldering</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>improvisation</category>
        
        <category>audiovisual</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Emute Lab 2 @ The Rosehill</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/Emutelab 2 Small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;EMuTeLab2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emute Lab presents: an evening of audiovisual experimentation, with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derek Holzer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Duff&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex Peverett&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;qgb&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rose Hill, Brighton, 19th October, 7:30pm-11pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£6 (£4 students, concessions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tickets are available in advance from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ticketsource.co.uk/date/552827&quot;&gt;https://www.ticketsource.co.uk/date/552827&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/2128610264080293/&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/events/2128610264080293/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;derek-holzer&quot;&gt;Derek Holzer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derek Holzer (USA 1972) is a sound + light artist based in Helsinki &amp;amp; Berlin, whose current interests include DIY electronics, audiovisual instrument building, the relationship between sound and space, media archaeology, and participatory art forms. He has performed live, taught workshops and created scores of unique instruments and installations since 2002 across Europe, North and South America, and New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/202910465&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://macumbista.net&quot;&gt;http://macumbista.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/macumbista&quot;&gt;https://vimeo.com/macumbista&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;andrew-duff&quot;&gt;Andrew Duff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Duff is a sound artist and organiser of the University of Sussex based Brighton Modular meet. Since the late 1980s, Andrew has amassed a large collection of electronic music, and collected, modified and experimented with a range of, generally, Japanese analogue synthesizers, DJing, recording music and performing live at club nights and various other events. Since completing a Masters in Design and Digital Media in 2000, he has been involved in teaching, academic research, and continues to develop his own work. Since 2012 his work has been largely based around the use of a eurorack modular synthesiser and modified Vectrex games console for audio/visual and performance based vector oscillographics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kzBtUrvw0Js&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://andrew-duff.co.uk/&quot;&gt;http://andrew-duff.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/allthesixes666/&quot;&gt;https://www.instagram.com/allthesixes666/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/halfofmeis333&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/user/halfofmeis333&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alexander-peverett&quot;&gt;Alexander Peverett&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander Peverett is a multi-disciplinary artist whose work explores the fields of electronic &amp;amp; computer music, video art, multi-media installation, procedural art and computer graphics. His audio work has been published on labels such as Skam, 12k, Line and Icasea. He is one part of Team Doyobi (Skam) and a member of Computers Club. His work has been shown at All Tomorrows Parties, Sonar, Bios, Lovebytes, the Tate Modern, the Pompidou Centre, the Los Angeles Museum of Contemporary Art, the New York Museum of the Moving Image and various other international festivals and institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander will be performing an iteration of “Reality Television” an ongoing experimental series of procedural audio-visual systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;qgb&quot;&gt;qgb&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;qgb is an an up and coming producer and artist local to Brighton. His work blends influences from his studies in audiovisual art at Sussex University with a love for UK dance music and its visceral quality. Exploring ideas from his debut album Hornets, the set combines algorithmic sequencing, hardware instruments and hyper-digital synthesis. Expect colourful soundscapes, treacherous rhythms, rumbling sub-bass, and striking visual accompaniments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tVzjqXOmJsE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/qgb/qgb-live-at-the-rose-hill&quot;&gt;https://soundcloud.com/qgb/qgb-live-at-the-rose-hill&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bleep.com/release/103083-qgb-hornets&quot;&gt;https://bleep.com/release/103083-qgb-hornets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab2</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>improvisation</category>
        
        <category>audiovisual</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Emute Lab 1 @ The Rosehill</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/emute1_webFlyer_noText_landscape_sm.png&quot; alt=&quot;EMuTeLab1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; :::::  May 23 - 7.30pm The Rosehill, Brighton :::::   &lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Emute Lab Presents … an evening of free strings and string free pedals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join us at The Rose Hill for a set of three duos from some of the UK’s fiercest improvisers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hannah Marshall (cello) &amp;amp; Otto Willberg (double bass)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seth Bennett (double bass) &amp;amp; Alice Eldridge (cello)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Noise Peddlar - Danny Bright &amp;amp; Lee Westwood - no input pedalboards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.therosehill.co.uk&quot;&gt;The Rose Hill&lt;/a&gt;, Brighton. £5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Emute Lab Presents …  is a space for sharing the ongoing research and practice of Emute Lab members and collaborators.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hannah Marshall (cello) &amp;amp; Otto Willberg (double bass)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A duo that has been finding an improvised language of rich sonic, textural and rhythmic counterpoint over the last year with performances at Fizzle - Birmingham, Bristol Music Club, Flim Flam - London and Fuse Arts Space - Bradford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hannah Marshall&lt;/b&gt;
I experiment with approaches to playing the ‘Cello using improvisation as a means to explore sound, music and performance. I play with a range of experimental groups and projects in the UK and Europe. I also collaborate with other performers and artists who work in mediums including theatre, performance, dance, storytelling and film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Ask your ears :] Exploring sonic territories and visiting musical antipodes, demonstrating an esoteric approach to instrumentation that is truly unique&lt;/em&gt;”- DreamCraeft recommendation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;with Marshall’s impeccable timing and skill for finding strong yet subtle gestures…&lt;/em&gt; ” “&lt;em&gt;..Vicious!.&lt;/em&gt;”- Dan Warburton&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Hannah Marshall has proven herself to be a solo player of imagination and intelligence; recording an album of deceptively simple but very rewarding and hypnotic music. A series of small meals that combine in a feast for the ears and mind.&lt;/em&gt;” - ears for eyes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/je2V2a53RYM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Otto Willberg&lt;/b&gt; is an improvising musician and composer, who mostly plays the double bass. His obsessive, and slightly unhinged tape Got Gills? is issued this July on Slip, and is his first release with the imprint. He plays with multiple groups around the UK, and has recently toured NYC and the States with guitarist David Birchall, and psych outfit Desmadrados Soldados de Ventura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GHU2jB5-mak&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Duot: Seth Bennett (double bass) &amp;amp; Alice Eldridge (cello)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Seth Bennett&lt;/b&gt; is one of the U.K.’s pre-eminent improvising double bass players. Currently based in rural Perthshire, his work involves free improvisation and composition for improvisers. Recent works include En Bas Quartet, a low string quartet for improvisers, all lovers are the song, a suite of six pieces for string trio and voice, and contributions to several recorded works, including CD releases by improvising sextet Sloth Racket, the Julie Tippets/Martin Archer Ensemble, Orchestre Tout Puissant Marcel Duchamp, and the large ensemble Favourite Animals. In addition, he maintains a busy performance schedule in Britain and across Europe in Jazz, Free Improvisation, English Folk music, and Contemporary Classical settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gFhNe-YtVm4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Alice Eldridge&lt;/b&gt; is a cellist and researcher working across sound, technology and ecology in scientific and creative domains. As an improvising cellist her intuitive, exploratory character has led to collaborations with some of europe’s most adventurous musicians at the  intersections of contemporary classical, folk, jazz, minimal pop, algorithmic and feedback musics. Recent collaborations and guest appearances include premiere performances of Seth Bennett’s En Bas Quartet, Julie Kjaer’s &lt;em&gt;This is Where You See Me&lt;/em&gt; and John Russell’s &lt;em&gt;The Narrative&lt;/em&gt;. She is 1/4 of all female multi-arts collective, Collectress, 1/2 of Feedback Cell, an ongoing experiment in open-ended hybrid luthiary and a regular at John Russell’s Fete Quaqua and Brighton’s Safehouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/180304450&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/api/player.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/180304450&quot;&gt;Alice Eldridge at Fete QuaQua 2016&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/user54602909&quot;&gt;Jack&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Noise Peddler&lt;/b&gt; (Danny Bright + Lee Westwood): two pedalboards, four amplifiers, and no inputs. Noise Peddler perform part-composed, part-improvised sounds generated and manipulated by guitar pedals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vXu1KTFuDdM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Danny Bright&lt;/b&gt; is a composer, sound designer, recordist, and sonic manipulator working across the fields of music, performance, installation, theatre and media. His practice explores the boundaries between sound/music/noise and space/place/memory; he is currently developing multi-modal compositional, performance, critical and installation work investigating sonic temporalities and auditory ‘ghostings’. Danny performs on guitar, samplescapes, tape, text/voice, and electronics as an ensemble member/leader, solo artist and improviser. He also works as a sound designer and composer for internationally recognised arts, theatre and media companies, and as a producer, recordist, sound technologist and engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Described by the Musician’s Union as “one of the UK’s most exciting and versatile musicians”, &lt;b&gt;Lee Westwood&lt;/b&gt; is a guitarist and composer whose wide-ranging output stems from a long-term tenacity for musical exploration. Far from ordinary, Lee’s works range from the Geometry-Music crossover of his multimedia exhibition ‘A Hidden Order’ (Saatchi Gallery, Athr, SCOPE) to a vast back-catalogue of works for solo guitar; from headlining festival stages with Hip-Hop groups and Prog Folk acts (Dizraeli &amp;amp; The Small Gods; Le Juki) to commissions from some of the UK’s leading ensembles and choirs (LSO, WUE; Musarc; Riot Ensemble; Notes Inégales). – &lt;a href=&quot;www.lee-westwood.com&quot;&gt;www.lee-westwood.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/emutelab1</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>improvisation</category>
        
        <category>NIME</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>EMuTeLab @ Seeing Sound - Report</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.seeingsound.co.uk&quot;&gt;Seeing Sound&lt;/a&gt; is a biannual symposium on audiovisual art, which took place at Bath Spa University in March.  This year two EMuTeLab members were presenting their work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;andrew-duff-i-dont-think-anyone-has-been-electrocuted-yet-sharing-info-online-to-modify-an-old-games-console-for-vector-oscillographics&quot;&gt;Andrew Duff: &lt;em&gt;I don’t think anyone has been electrocuted yet: Sharing info online to modify an old games console for vector oscillographics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/duff_seeingsound.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Andrew Duff presentation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract: &lt;em&gt;Since sharing a pdf online about how to modify a Vectrex (an early 1980s vector-based games console) to directly take in three audio signals to draw directly on the screen as one would with an oscilloscope, I have unwittingly become a ‘go-to guy’ with regards to entering the world of vector oscillographics. I have since been invited to talk at various electronic music events and am regularly contacted with requests for support, information and recommendations on appropriate modules. All the while the games console itself becomes harder to find on the second-hand market as they are perhaps becoming something of a cult artefact sought after by both gamers and electronic artists/musicians alike.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Vectrex offers a unique visual experience rarely found in standard oscilloscopes; it utilises three inputs for x, y and z control of the electron beam, is monochromatic, and the screen is relatively large. It does, however have its own idiosyncrasies, which makes for an interesting tool to work and perform with.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This talk will present a brief contextual history of experiments in this field with some examples of influential oscillographic artists such as Ben Laposky &amp;amp; Herbert W. Franke, followed by an overview of the impact sharing this pdf has had with examples of work by a range of current artists, experimentalists and performers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew’s talk was part of a wider Vectrex theme at Seeing Sound, with other presentations from Derek Holzer and Douglas Nunn.  You can find his slides on his website &lt;a href=&quot;http://users.sussex.ac.uk/~ad207/adweb/assets/seeingsound2018slides.pdf&quot;&gt;http://users.sussex.ac.uk/~ad207/adweb/assets/seeingsound2018slides.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chris-kiefer-10k-video&quot;&gt;Chris Kiefer: &lt;em&gt;10K Video&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/10kvideo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chris Kiefer 10K Video&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;10000 neural oscillators conspire to make a bad approximation of a one second video loop, while their internal networks are stretched and twisted by their own sound and their neighbours.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an improvised performance, where a video is resynthesised by an ensemble of neural conceptor networks, each of which has learnt (with varying degrees of success) to approximate the behaviour of an individual pixel in the original.  The ghostly result is manipulated live, to send this mass of miniature feedback systems into collective overdrive.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neural networks used in this piece are complex dynamical systems which need self-sustaining energy to continue their role; they follow a trajectory, but this trajectory can be manipulated and influenced, both between networks and from global forces; these networks can be damped, overdriven, distorted, leaked, excited, surprised, saturated and revitalised.  When revitalised in synchrony they can play a rendition of the original video loop.  When manipulated, this video can be distorted and effected in many directions.  During the piece, the host of networks are continually revitalised, and then manipulated along infinity varying trajectories towards noise or destruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris performed this new piece live.  You can see a generative version that runs in your web browser at &lt;a href=&quot;http://facingaway.luuma.net/&quot;&gt;http://facingaway.luuma.net/&lt;/a&gt; (fairly decent GPU needed)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/seeingsoundreport</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/seeingsoundreport</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>talk</category>
        
        <category>audiovisual</category>
        
        <category>music</category>
        
        <category>graphics</category>
        
        <category>machine learning</category>
        
        <category>vectrex</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ens Ekt Improvisation Workshop</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/260582432&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/260582432&quot;&gt;Ens Ekt @ SARC 1&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/user7828804&quot;&gt;Paul Stapleton&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; :::::  Friday June 1st,  1pm - 3pm @ Sussex Humanities Lab :::::   &lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ens Ekt will be visiting us as part of their UK tour for a practice based workshop on the nature and relevance for improvisation in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is improvisation?&lt;/em&gt;  We’re interested in what you think. How is it relevant for your own practice (regardless of discipline)? And how can you develop potential?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop format is liable to be subject to improvisation, but will likely follow a format such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ens Ekt will play an improvised set.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There will then be an open conversation concerning practice and improvisation, facilitated by the trio.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open Session. There will then be a session in which all are welcome to participate. As well as musicians we positively encourage those from other areas of interest (perhaps dance, drama, visual art or any other area).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event is free, but please register at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/ens-ekt-improvisation-workshop-emute-lab-tickets-45646588174&quot;&gt;eventbrite&lt;/a&gt; as spaces are limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adam Pultz Melbye&lt;/strong&gt; – double bass&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Simon Rose&lt;/strong&gt; – baritone saxophone&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Paul Stapleton&lt;/strong&gt; – bonsai sound sculpture (BoSS)  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ens Ekt features the experimental musical inventions of Paul Stapleton (Californian born, Belfast-based) placed in dialogue with the circular breathed multiphonics and harmonic textures of Simon Rose (English born, Berlin-based) and the resonant gestural and spectrally focused playing of Adam Pultz Melbye (Danish born, Berlin-based). The group explores emergent timbral, dynamic and social musical structures through improvisation. Having worked together more frequently in duo settings (see below), the trio configuration offers an opportunity to explore new modes of interactions in part facilitated by purpose built technologies that intertwine metallic, wooden and electronic resonances in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.paulstapleton.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/Ens-Ekt-01-900x450.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ensekt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ens Ekt will be playing a full set at &lt;a href=&quot;http://safehousebrighton.co.uk/2018/05/31/ens-ekt/&quot;&gt;Safehouse&lt;/a&gt; on May 31st.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/ensekt</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/ensekt</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>improvisation</category>
        
        <category>NIME</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Newhaven Soundcamp</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/westbeach.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;soundcamp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; :::::  May 5th - May 6th @ Newhaven Community Garden, Newhaven :::::   &lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join us for newhaven soundcamp over the International Dawn Chorus weekend of 5th to 6th May 2018, when small groups of people around the world will sleep outside and listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International Dawn Chorus Day is a world wide celebration of the dawn chorus initiated by the Wildlife Trusts to raise awareness of the deep importance of nature conservation and close relationship between human wellbeing and that of all other living species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newhaven Soundcamp is part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundtent.org/soundcamp_reveil.html&quot;&gt;REVEIL&lt;/a&gt;, an network of open mics around the world. Instigated by arts collective &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundtent.org/soundcamp_about.html&quot;&gt;soundcamp&lt;/a&gt;, REVEIL curates a live radio broadcast from these listening points as the sun rises around the globe on the International Dawn Chorus weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newhaven Soundcamp is a small scale event for local residents to act as a simple, potent point for ecological, social, intellectual, aesthetic and spiritual engagement with the soundscape of Newhaven. It links this spot on Sussex Downs Biosphere (The Living Coast) to an international network of site of ecological and sonic interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The broadcast will be made using a DIY radio transmitter constructed from a raspberry Pi and will feature on the Resonance FM broadcast early on Sunday morning - or check out links below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Links:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/soundcamp-newhaven-tickets-45174650596&quot;&gt;Further information and free tickets&lt;/a&gt; for Newhaven Soundcamp&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://soundtent.org/soundcamp_listen.html&quot;&gt;listen to the curated stream on International Dawn Chorus Day&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Listen in to the Newhaven mic on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://locusonus.org/soundmap/051/&quot;&gt;locussonus sound map&lt;/a&gt; - this will be streaming all weekend&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More about &lt;a href=&quot;soundtent.org&quot;&gt;Soundcamp&lt;/a&gt; and links other soundcamps around the world&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://paper.dropbox.com/doc/Streaming-Workshop-Brighton-Digital-Festival-Onca-Gallery-12-10-17-0SoIwneySy7FLeixfsveP&quot;&gt;Information on building your own DIY radio transmitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://paper.dropbox.com/doc/Solar-power-for-off-grid-streaming-JF9LIMXwqMeH19twsrX3U&quot;&gt;Further info on solar panels for off grid streaming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelivingcoast.org.uk&quot;&gt;The Living Coast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://growingtogethernewhaven.org/&quot;&gt;Newhaven Community garden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 3, Prof Almo Farina will be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.emutelab.org/blog/almoFarina&quot;&gt;giving a talk&lt;/a&gt; on his pioneering work in Ecoacoustics - all welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented in association with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelivingcoast.org.uk/&quot;&gt;The Living Coast&lt;/a&gt;, kindly hosted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://growingtogethernewhaven.org/&quot;&gt;Growing Together Newhaven&lt;/a&gt; and supported by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/shl/&quot;&gt;Sussex Humanities Lab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/soundcamp</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/soundcamp</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>ecoacoustics</category>
        
        <category>DIY tech</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Seminar: Gianluca Memoli and Spyros Polychronopoulos (Interact Lab, Informatics)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;::::: Thursday, April 26th, 2018. 2-4pm - Recital Room (Falmer House 120) :::::&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two talks from members of the Interact Lab at Sussex, who are both researchers in Acoustic Levitation and Human Computer Interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spyros-polychronopoulos-new-ways-to-create-and-deliver-music&quot;&gt;Spyros Polychronopoulos: New ways to create and deliver music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/spolychronopoulos.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spyros Polychronopoulos&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aesthetics of dead (as pre-recorded) and live (as endless unique reproduced) music. Challenging the “here and now” of the work of art with programmable performers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/reference/subject/philosophy/works/ge/benjamin.htmhttps://www.marxists.org/reference/subject/philosophy/works/ge/benjamin.htm&quot;&gt;Walter Benjamin (1936)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://emporium.room40.org/products/583176-spyros-polychronopoulos-live-electronic-music-sound-object&quot;&gt;Live Electronic Music Sound Object (2016)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/docs/Music perception and the fluctuation of utopia.pdf&quot;&gt;Music perception and the fluctuation of utopia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bio&quot;&gt;Bio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spyros Polychronopoulos was born in Athens, Greece in 1980. His interest in sound, both as a physical phenomenon as well as a form of art, began at an early age. He holds a degree in Physics and a PhD in Electrical Engineering from University of Patras, Greece. His thesis focused on tuning the acoustics of closed spaces and he has published a number of papers in this field. After relocating to London in 2014, he gained three years of practical experience working as an acoustic consultant. Further to his research in sound, he has developed unique sound objects, released 15 albums and performed a number of concerts around the world. Spyros regularly leads workshops and lectures discussing the new technologies in composition and aesthetics of sound. He currently works as a Research Fellow in the Informatics Department at the University of Sussex, UK, researching ‘Human-computer Interaction for Acoustic Levitation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gianluca-memoli-spatial-sound-using-meta-materials&quot;&gt;Gianluca Memoli: Spatial Sound using Meta-materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/gmemoli.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gianluca Memoli&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an architect, a sound engineer or a theatre director designs the acoustics of a space, the presence of sound is binary: it is either there for everyone or not. We manage light differently, though: well-established technologies allows us to exploit light and shadows, beams that follow characters, diffused or focused spotlights. The technology for achieving similar results with sound is simply not there: since directional speakers still don’t maintain their promises in terms of performance, large arrays of speakers are still used for beam-forming, either software controlled or spatially arranged. In this talk, I will discuss the opportunities offered by acoustic meta-materials to achieve spatial control on sound in static applications. These can be placed in front of loudspeakers just like lenses or filters would be positioned in front of a light source, for achieving diffraction-limited effects. I will also discuss where, in my opinion, these new tools may lead us in the short and medium term and whether they will eventually give us the same control on sound that we have on light, across all the frequency range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bio-1&quot;&gt;Bio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gianluca has worked in acoustics for 14 years, after his PhD. His acoustic research (soundscapes, industrial and medical ultrasound) has taken him to influence EU legislation and ISO standards, to work with local authorities and hospitals, to measure the largest bubble in the word and to find new ways to prolong shelf life of honey using ultrasound. He is a passionate science communicator and has worked with creatives of all sorts, from garden designers to choreographers.  As a newly appointed lecturer in Informatics at Sussex, he is currently looking at ways to give creatives the same control on sound that they have on light using specially engineered, 3D-printed, passive materials.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/interactLabSeminar</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/interactLabSeminar</guid>
        
        <category>emutelab</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>talk</category>
        
        <category>acoustics</category>
        
        <category>3D printing</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
